<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon Mr. Baxter's last book, entituled, The English non-conformity, as under King Charles II and King James II truly stated and argued in a letter to a friend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52853</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13114099</idno>
  <idno type="VID">97725</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240861019</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing N51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10673</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13114099</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52853)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 746:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon Mr. Baxter's last book, entituled, The English non-conformity, as under King Charles II and King James II truly stated and argued in a letter to a friend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Clavil ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signed: N.N.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  English nonconformity.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON Mr. <hi>BAXTER</hi>'s Last BOOK, ENTITULED, <hi>The English Non-conformity,</hi> AS UNDER King <hi>CHARLES</hi> II. and King <hi>JAMES</hi> II. Truly Stated and Argued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a Letter to a Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>I labour for Peace, but when I speak unto them thereof: they make them ready to Battle,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 120.6.</hi> Old Translation.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Clavil,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in <hi>St. Pauls Church-Yard.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:2"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON Mr. <hi>BAXTER</hi>'s Last BOOK, ENTITULED, <hi>The English Non-Conformity,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:97725:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97725:4"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON <hi>Mr. Baxter's</hi> Last BOOK.</head>
            <head type="sub">In a LETTER to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen you sent me Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s New Book into the Country, you desired my thoughts concerning it in a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I hope you did not mean that I should write you an Answer to it; if you did, I must tell you, that you did not look into the Book, nor read the <hi>Title-Page</hi> it self, if you expected such a performance from me; alas, Sir, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Books are not so easily answered. He tells you him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self that his Books are <hi>of Ʋnconfutable Defence,</hi> that they cannot be answered, and would you have me to offer to answer Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book, when he himself assures us before-hand that <hi>his Books cannot be Answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:</hi> No Sir, I am too wise to attempt it, especially since
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97725:5"/>such Men as the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> have ventured to so little purpose to meddle with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Books, while they were of <hi>Ʋnconfutable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> and Unanswerable. And now I have mentioned the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> I cannot do less than pitty some late great mistakes of his with all my heart; tho the World allow Him to be as well qualified by his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Learning as any Person to defend the Church of <hi>England</hi> against the Adversaries on both sides, and think him to have so much skill as to distinguish be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Books that <hi>might</hi> be Answered, and Books <hi>that could not;</hi> yet He has of late Years had the great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happiness to encounter with Adversaries, that wrote nothing but <hi>Demonstration</hi> and <hi>Ʋnconfutable Books,</hi> and to foyl himself with venturing out against such Writers. I believe the <hi>Dean</hi> will not hastily forget his Popish Adversary Mr. <hi>John Sergeant,</hi> who run him down at such a strange rate with <hi>first Principles,</hi> and one <hi>Demonstration</hi> upon the back of another, and baffled him just at the rate Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> did: all which might have been saved, had Mr. <hi>Dean</hi> been but as cautious as I am, had He but taken these two Invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Mens words, as I do. I would no more venture upon Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> with his <hi>Ʋnconfutable Books,</hi> than upon Mr. <hi>Sergeant,</hi> that up and down his <hi>Letter to the Continuator of the present State of the Controversie,</hi> tells the Reader, that his Books <hi>cannot be disprov'd,</hi> that it is an <hi>impossible task</hi> to answer them.
<note place="margin">In the Preface.</note>
               <hi>I am told</hi> (says Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>by divers, that I have written enough already on these Subjects, were it only my first and second Plea,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The best Witts of our Nation</hi> (says Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi> in the same Letter) <hi>Men not a jot inferiour to your great Doctor himself</hi> [Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi>] <hi>have not only read those Letters of mine</hi> [his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97725:5"/>five <hi>Catholick</hi> Letters as he calls them against Doctor <hi>Stillingfleet.</hi>] <hi>but given such a Character of them for <hi>Vnanswerable</hi> as is not Modest for me to repeat.</hi> Now I am satisfied to let two such men alone, and dare no more Answer Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> than Mr. <hi>Sergeant,</hi> especially when I find what pittiful Work they made of it, that were so hardy to write against either of these two <hi>Invinsible</hi> Champions. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of some of his Writings against the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> says, <hi>I hnow not of any one of these that are Answered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 3.</note>
               <hi>or any thing like an Answer to them Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, save that to some part of the first</hi> (to wit his Plea for Peace) <hi>some <hi>meer Impertinent Noise</hi> was made by <hi>some one</hi> that is confuted.</hi> This is very great and lofty indeed, and yet his invincible Brother-Champion <hi>John Sergeant</hi> can talk full as bigg; espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> or the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">See Letter to the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.</note> come in his way.</p>
            <p>And yet as loftily as these two Champions Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> talk of their own performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and of their great Victories over the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> I dare appeal to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Conscience, that he does believe that the <hi>Dean</hi> hath fully confuted all <hi>John Sergeant</hi>'s <hi>Pleas</hi> for <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> and to Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi>'s Conscience, that the <hi>Dean</hi> had done as much for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Pleas</hi> for <hi>Nonconformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Sir, I hope will satisfie you that you ought to expect no answer to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book from me, but if it will not alone, I have a Reason or two more for you, one is, That all that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath offered in this Book of Argument, hath been Answered over and over again by his Answerers, the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> and tho' he be not ashamed to transcribe himself, and to teaze the World with the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97725:6"/>same Reasons over again, yet others are to imitate him in transcribing their Answers to him. Another Reason is, because the World have given up Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> as well as his Brother <hi>John Sergeant</hi> as incurable, upon whom good Advice as well as good Arguments are equally lost. I look upon these two to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Reverse of one another, that Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi> is the <hi>Popish</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> the <hi>Protestant John Sergeant,</hi> they are in every thing so exactly the same; their cause is the same, Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi>'s bustle for <hi>Oral Tradition</hi> being every jot as good as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s for Non-Conformity; their management is the same, the one writes as voluminously as the other, the one hath the same Art of doing it that the other by Transcribing his own self, and by infinite Tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy and splitting of Divisions; the one Writes as dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically as the other. In a word, They write De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration alike, they talk sense alike, and they have had of late, I believe I may say success alike in making the World weary of reading their Writings.</p>
            <p>Another Reason I have for not Answering Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Book, because I am affraid he is so fond of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, and so resolute for his own Opinions, that he will not vouchsafe to read his Adversaries Books, and I have not so much time upon my hands as to throw it away upon an Answer to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> which will be thrown aside by him without once reading it. I have reason to believe that this is become of late his temper; since in this very Book of his you sent me, he says, nothing had been Answered to a certain Book of his, whereas his meaning should be, that he had not, or would not read the Answer to it. Speaking (Page 2d. and 3d.) of his <hi>Plea for Peace,</hi> and his <hi>full <hi>Treatise of Episcopacy,</hi>
               </hi> and his <hi>Apology,</hi> and his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97725:6"/>
               <hi>Second Plea for Peace,</hi> and <hi>Treatise of Church Concord,</hi> He very gravely adds, <hi>I know not of any one of these that are Answered, or any thing like an Answer to them Written, save that to some part of the first</hi> [to wit the <hi>Plea for Peace</hi>] <hi>Some meer impertinent Noise was made by some one that is Answered:</hi> and yet you and I have read, and I dare say Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himself has seen a Book Printed seven Years ago with this Title,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Printed for</hi> Moses Pitt, 1682.</note>
               <hi>A Vindication of the Primitive Church and Diocesan Episcopacy, in Answer to Mr.</hi> Baxter<hi>'s Church-History of Bishops and their Councils abridged: <hi>As also to some part of his Treatise of Episcopacy.</hi>
               </hi> If you remember that Book, but especially the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> to it, you are able to give another Reason beside forgetfulness, why Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> takes no notice of that <hi>Answer</hi> to <hi>Part</hi> of his <hi>Treatise of Episcopacy;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance never was Man's Picture better taken than Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s is in the Preface to that Book; whoever would know Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and take his height, need only read that Preface and Book, and I am confident that would Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himself but read the Preface it self twice over with calmness and deliberation, he would never set Pen to Paper more in Controversie. You have now, Sir, the rest of my Reasons why you should not expect, nor I write an Answer to this Book, however I will not return you the Book without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing some few Reflections upon it, much fewer than it does deserve.</p>
            <p>As I read the Book over, I could not but very much pity the Author of it, He complains in his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-Page, That Rulers and Clergy want <hi>Willingness and Patience to read and hear their just defence;</hi> I do assure Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> that I had <hi>Willingness and Patience</hi> to read his Book through, and I can assure him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97725:7"/>that tho' I was necessitated (as you very well know) to read a great many untoward Books in the late Controversie against Popery, yet that the reading of his Book was a greater exercise of my patience than even the <hi>Replyes</hi> and the <hi>Defences</hi> of the <hi>Represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sergeant</hi> himself: All which was because I found Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book to be liable to these follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reflections.</p>
            <p>That it was one of the most unnecessary, unseaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and unaccountable Books, that hath been Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed to my knowledge in this Age.</p>
            <p>Every one of these Reflections may be easily justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and it may be done in the compass of a Letter. That this new Book of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was <hi>Vnnecessary,</hi> every one will grant that hath acquainted himself with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s former Books, because he can find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here but the bare repetition of his old Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Reasons for Non-Conformity; it is too se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere an imposition upon the World in Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> to put them upon buying this his <hi>New Book,</hi> which hath nothing new in it, upon reading this as new, which they that are acquainted in his works have read in them so often before. I will go no further back than the Books he hath written within these last ten Years, and I need instance hardly in any else than his <hi>Pleas for Peace;</hi> would it be worth the trouble to transcribe the harmony that is betwixt <hi>those Books,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath now Published, or indeed were any of it worth the reading when done, I could shew how very unnecessary this new Book of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s was. But in defence of him it will be urged perhaps, That tho indeed the Matter of this New Book be the very same with his first <hi>Plea for Peace,</hi> for example, yet that the Arguments are improved,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97725:7"/>and that <hi>more Reasons</hi> for <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> are urged in <hi>this Book</hi> than in <hi>that,</hi> which had but <hi>Thirty Reasons</hi> for the <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> of <hi>Ministers,</hi> and <hi>Six</hi> for <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> whereas this <hi>New Book</hi> hath <hi>Forty</hi> for <hi>Ministers,</hi> and <hi>Twelve Reasons</hi> for <hi>Laymens</hi> Non-Conformity. This is all the defence that can be made for him, and this is a very pleasant one, a Man would suspect from this that our <hi>Church</hi> hath since the Year 1680. been adding new terms of Communion, and that Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hath found <hi>Ten</hi> unreasonable ones among those im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon <hi>Ministers,</hi> which they cannot with a good Conscience conform to, and <hi>Six</hi> among those impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed upon the <hi>Laity:</hi> but since there hath been no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of alteration in the Terms of our Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion since the Year 1680, saving that there is <hi>one acknowledged Reason</hi> for Non-Conformity <hi>less</hi> by the <hi>Declaration against the Obligation of the Solemn League and Covenant, being</hi> not required after <hi>March</hi> 1682. How comes it to pass that there were but <hi>Thirty Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> for the <hi>Ministers</hi> and <hi>Six</hi> for the <hi>Laymens</hi> Non-Conformity in 1680, and yet that 1683, [for in that year Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> wrote this Book, tho' he did not Publish it till this Year 1689.] the <hi>Ministers</hi> were grown up to <hi>Forty,</hi> and the <hi>Laymens</hi> to <hi>Twelve?</hi> I can for my part see no other reason for it, but that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was pleased to have it so, who may by this art and humour gratifie the World if he pleases two Years hence with another new <hi>
                  <hi>English Non-Conformity,</hi> as under KING</hi> WILLIAM <hi>and QƲEEN</hi> MARY <hi>truly stated and argued by Richard Baxter,</hi> without any other trouble than on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly varying the phrase of this Book a little, and split<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his <hi>Forty Ministers</hi> Reasons for Non-Conformity into <hi>Eighty,</hi> or a <hi>Hundred,</hi> and his <hi>Laymens Twelve</hi> into
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97725:8"/>
               <hi>Twenty-four,</hi> or what other Number can please him better. As for the Arguments being improved in this <hi>New Book</hi> further than they were in his <hi>former,</hi> they are indeed improved in one respect, they are embel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht with a great deal more of gaul and indecent pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and irreverence towards all sorts of Persons, and towards the most Sacred of things in the Church, I mean one of the Sacraments, than his <hi>Plea for Peace</hi> was; and this <hi>Plea</hi> was none of the modestest or mildest Books, as any one must own that will either look into the Book it self, or read the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> Character of it in his <hi>Preface to the Ʋnreasonableness of Separation; under the name</hi> (says he) <hi>of <hi>A Plea for Peace,</hi> out comes a Book, which far better deserved the Title of <hi>A Plea for Disorder and Separation,</hi> not without frequent, sharp and bitter Reflections on the Constitution of our Church and the Conformity required; as though it had been design'd on purpose to represent the Clergy of our Church, as a company of notorious Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Perjured Villains, for conforming to the Laws of the Land, and Orders established among us;</hi> whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will be at the pains to compare that <hi>Plea for Peace</hi> and this <hi>New Book</hi> of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s together, will see reasons enough to justifie Mr. <hi>Dean</hi>'s Character of <hi>that Book,</hi> and <hi>mine</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> that they differ in nothing else, but that the new one hath more frequent, more sharp and bitter Reflections than the other; as if the older Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> grew, his Passion and Severity were the greater, and the nearer he was to his Grave, he did with the greater earnestness wreak his spite and anger at our Church, resolving to leave (as I am affraid the <hi>Dean</hi> said too prophetically of him) <hi>his Life and Sting together in her wounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:97725:8"/>
            <p>But now we are talking of the number of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons for Non-Conformity, it were almost worth the while to give you a list of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s in this <hi>New Book,</hi> some of which are very extraordinary, as <hi>his</hi> 34th. for instance, about <hi>renouncing all Obligation from the Covenant to endeavour any alteration of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> which it seems is a Reason for Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in 1689, tho' that <hi>Declaration</hi> ceased by <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> in <hi>March,</hi> 1682. But since that would be tedious, I will entertain you with the management of <hi>two</hi> of his <hi>Ministers</hi> reasons, and <hi>one</hi> of his <hi>Laymens</hi> for Separation.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Sixth Point</hi> of Non-Conformity is the <hi>Article of Baptized Infants Salvation:</hi> This is grounded upon that little Rubrick at the end of the Office for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Baptism, <hi>It is certain by Gods Word, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which are Baptized, dying before they commit actual Sin are undoubtedly saved:</hi> and this little <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> he makes most Tragical work about, Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> will have it to be <hi>a New Article of Faith,</hi> will have the <hi>Assertion</hi> to be <hi>arrogant and divisive,</hi> that it is <hi>false,</hi> and that it is a <hi>dangerous adding to the Word of God. We dare not</hi> (says Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> when he is grown hot in the Argument) <hi>father that on God which he never spake, and we dread the Curse,</hi> Rev. 22. <hi>against them that shall add to his Word,</hi> viz. <hi>That he will add <hi>His Curses</hi> upon them.—This is to <hi>belie God,</hi> and to <hi>take His Name in vain.</hi> And for Nine Thousand or Ten Thousand Ministers to affirm, That this</hi> is certain by God's Word that they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly saved, <hi>and when they have done cannot to this day shew us one Word of God that saith it, is such an adding to his Word, as we had rather still be called all that's naught, and Imprison'd, than be guilty of,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97725:9"/>just after, he is so fierce that he delares, that if all the other hard terms of Communion were taken off, that tho' the other Thirty-Nine <hi>Ministers Reasons</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and this little <hi>Rubrick</hi> left alone, he would not conform. <hi>Should we lye</hi> (saith Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>) <hi>to be conformable, were there <hi>but this one thing it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to Non-Conformity whatever we suffer for it.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's a tast for you of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Spirit, and the management of his cause in this <hi>New Book,</hi> you see he does not his business by halves, tho' I must needs say he might have spared himself the trouble of the rest of his Book besides this Chapter, since I think he has done the Church's and the whole Clergy's bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness effectually in it, he has proved not only the whole Body of the Clergy of this Church at present, but all that have Conformed since 1662, to be a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Cursed Liars</hi> and <hi>Forsworn,</hi> and that the Church doth make that a term of her Communion, which Men cannot assent too without <hi>belying God,</hi> and <hi>taking His Name in vain,</hi> and drawing <hi>down his Curses upon them.</hi> And this I will bear Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> witness if it were well proved, were enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him and all his Brethren Non-Conformists. When you read this, I know you will be apt to say the Man raves, and should be put into a dark room, and kept from Pen, Ink and Paper, and I cannot but think that too many more will be of your mind, when they see what very little occasion for all this bitter language Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> had: There is nothing more requisite herein, than to have these two points stated. 1. Whether Infants are capable Subjects of Baptism, and 2ly. By whose right it is that they are capable. That Infants are capable Subjects of Baptism Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97725:9"/>does not deny, nor ought, since he knows that it was the Practise of the Christian Church to Baptize In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants from the very beginning of it, and that we read in the <hi>New-Testament</hi> it self of <hi>whole Families</hi> being Baptized, and therefore it was a pittiful shift in Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and such as he was driven to meerly by the badness of his Cause to say,
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Pag. 50.</note>
               <hi>The most antient Churches were so much imployed in Baptizing the adult converted from Infidelity, that we read little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing expresly, and particularly what they did about In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in Baptism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Second thing is of more consequence, <hi>by whose Right it is, that Infants are capable of Baptism,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> indeed will have it by the Parents Right, that their being the Seed of Believers, entitles them to the priviledg of entring into Covenant with God by Baptism, but he has been told, and it has been proved often enough to him, that if <hi>Ministers</hi> must Baptize none but the Children of such Parents as are Believers, or have true Faith, they must Baptize none at all, since they cannot tell what Parents have true Faith, and what have not; and since they are not able to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the Hypocrite from the true Believer, and God only, and not they, does know the Hearts of Men. This Opinion of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> as it makes Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism impracticable, so was never own'd by the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, which makes Infants Right to Baptism to be not upon account either of their Parents Faith, or their own, but upon the Churches Power: The Church of God received the Power of the Keys from God, the chief Exercise of which Power of the Keys, is by admitting capable Subjects to remission of Sins by Baptism; the Church hath always admitted all Ages to the benefit of Baptism, the adult upon their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97725:10"/>own Profession of Faith, and entring into Covenant with God, Infants upon the Sponsors entring into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant for them, and undertaking for their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Conditions of it when they arrived to years of discretion.
<note place="margin">Eipstola ad Bonifacium.</note> And if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> would but read that Epistle of his own admired St. <hi>Austin,</hi> which the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> directed him to, he would let fall his unreasonable, I had almost said his uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable Controversie against the poor Children of Wicked or Prophane, or even Atheistical or Heathen Parents who are Gods Creatures, as well as the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Faithful, who are capable of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation as well as the other, and who have been by the Church of God (more Charitable than Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> herein) admitted, as well as the other to the means of Salvation upon Sponsors engaging for them.</p>
            <p>Since then Infants are capable of Baptism, and the Christian Church by virtue of the Keys, hath Power to admit all Infants to Remission of Sins by Baptism, and hath from the beginning of the Church admitted In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to this Privilege, upon their Sponsors engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for them, it is now time to answer Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> question, with which he makes so much noise, <hi>where it is said either expresly, or by consequence in Scripture,</hi> that <hi>Infants Baptized, dying before they commit actual Sin, are undoubtedly saved:</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> tells us, That <hi>All that ever by Talk he could hear was, Gal.</hi> 3.26, 27. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. and <hi>John</hi> 3.35. and these Texts he tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs over as not to the purpose; it is not worth while to enter the lists with him in defence of them, but instead of it, I will tell him where he might have read, and I fancy he has read two other Texts together, which I think are enough to satisfie any one but him that shuts his eyes.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97725:10"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Comber</hi> in his excellent Explications upon the Office of Baptism
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Page 179.</note> hath put them into an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s sake I will transcribe here. <hi>And that it may not be neglected, we are taught, That</hi> it is certain by Gods Word that Children Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, dying before they commit actual Sin, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly saved: <hi>For it is certain by Gods Word, that Baptism is appointed for Remission of Sins,</hi> Acts 2.38, and 22.16. <hi>And it is also certain, that all they whose Sins are forgiven are undoubtedly saved,</hi> Psal. 32.1. <hi>But Infants have no other Sin but their Original cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which being remitted in Baptism, they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly saved:</hi> And the Learned Docter adds, That <hi>it is plain, the first Christians believed the same Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and <hi>that the Fathers of the Second Council of</hi> Carthage <hi>did anathematise <hi>those that say, Children are not by Baptism delivered from Hell-fire, and made Partakers of Eternal Life.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that we have produced <hi>our Word of God out of two Texts,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> cannot say are either ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure or ambigious, and that it was so easy to shew the certainty of Baptized Infants Salvation from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and that this was the Doctrine of the first Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians about them, it were easie for me to turn the Tables upon Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and to make such reflecting abusive Questions, as he has done to the <hi>Youths from the Ʋniversities,</hi> to the <hi>raw ignorant Fellows or Lads</hi> as he calls the Clergy, and to treat him at the same rude scornful contemptuous rate, that he hath treated the whole body of our Clergy, upon far better Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons than he had, but it raises too great an indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to read such scurrility to be guilty of it, and I thank God, I have not so Learned Christ Jesus.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97725:11"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Ninth Reason for Non-Conformity is the <hi>Cross in Baptism,</hi> which he will needs have to be made a <hi>Sacrament</hi> by our Church. In his <hi>Plea for Peace</hi> he had taken some pains to prove it a Sacrament
<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<hi>'s Plea for Peace,</hi> p. 177, 178, &amp;c.</note> and the <hi>Dean of Pauls</hi> in his <hi>Ʋnreasonableness of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> took some to Convince him of the contrary. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> sinds in it every one of the parts of a true Sacrament, and the <hi>Dean</hi> shewed that he was grosly mistaken in every one of them. As for the <hi>outward Sign</hi> of this <hi>Baxterian</hi> (for I know no other name to distinguish it by) <hi>Sacrament,</hi> which he made to be <hi>the transient Image of the Cross used in Gods Service,</hi> Mr. <hi>Dean</hi> shewed him that this outward visible Sign was no part of Divine Worship, nor used as such in Gods Service, either as instituted by God or Man for that end; and as to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>second use</hi> of it, that the Signing with the Cross is used <hi>in our Baptismal Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting with God,</hi> the <hi>Dean</hi> shewed him that it was not, the Baptism being compleated before it, and without it the Covenanting Questions and Answers being over, and the Act of Baptizing, which seals and finishes the Baptismal Covenant being ended before the Sign of the Cross is used in the <hi>Office of Baptism.</hi> In Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>New Book</hi> he has got a solution to the <hi>Dean</hi>'s Answer, to <hi>his being told that Baptism is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect without it,</hi> his answer is, <hi>So it is without the Lord's-Supper, and yet that is justly added,</hi> which is a notable answer, but has not one grain of weight in it, for how is the Lord's-Supper added to Baptism, as a part of Baptism, or is not Baptism compleat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, or is it used in our <hi>Baptismal Covenanting.</hi> Let but Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> look at <hi>these Questions</hi> and <hi>his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer,</hi> and he will be ashamed of it, and he himself al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most thinks it as weak as we can, for he next backs it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97725:11"/>with a wise saying, <hi>It saith not that Man's Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God is perfect without it;</hi> if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> means here the <hi>Baptismal Covenanting with God,</hi> The <hi>Dean</hi> prov'd it him, that the Baptismal Covenant was perfected and over before the Cross is used; if he speaks of any <hi>other Covenant with God</hi> by the <hi>Sign of the Cross;</hi> the <hi>Dean</hi> shew'd him, that there is no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant at all made with God by the Sign of the Cross used in our Baptismal Office.</p>
            <p>But to return to Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Plea for Peace, he finds another Note of the Sacrament in the Cross, <hi>viz. The thing signified by the receiving of it, that we do as Covenanters, profess and oblige our selves not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed to confess the Faith of Christ Crucified and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> &amp;c. Here the <hi>Dean</hi> shewed him that the Nature of a Sacrament, is not only to <hi>signifie,</hi> but to <hi>convey</hi> the <hi>Grace</hi> signified by the <hi>Outward Sign;</hi> and that no grace nor benefit was pretended to be conveyed to the Child signed with the Cross, which was a naked Ceremony. Next Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> says, That <hi>the Minister speaks as Gods Officer from Him</hi> [when he Signs the Person Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized] <hi>and doth as Christ's Minister dedicate him by this Sign to the Service of Him who died upon the Cross.</hi> In answer to all which Mr. <hi>Dean</hi> shew'd him first, that the Minister doth not speak as God's Officer from him here, but that he speaks in the name of the Church, which is plain enough from the words used, <hi>WE re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive into the Congregation of Christ,</hi> &amp;c. and that the Signing with the Cross, was a token not <hi>to God</hi> but <hi>to Men,</hi> that the Person who had received that Sign upon his Forehead, had engaged himself to the Congregation (into which he was now admitting) that he would live as became the Disciple of a Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Redeemer: So that here was no dedicating of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97725:12"/>Person signed to God, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> falsely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stands the Practice and Design of the Church, but a Sign betwixt Man and Man; or a Significant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to declare to Men, that he that wears this Badge, is under such or such an Obligation to that Church to which he belongs; and this the <hi>Dean</hi> prov'd to him, was no more, than if after Baptism in an Independent Congregation, the Person to be admitted a Member of their Church, should be obliged to hold up his hand in token of his owning their Church Covenant, and obliging himself to live as a Church Member ought to do.</p>
            <p>I have been so very particular in giving this account of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Arguments against our use of the <hi>Sign of the Cross,</hi> out of his <hi>Plea for Peace,</hi> and a <hi>Breviate</hi> of the <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> direct and full answers to them, because Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was not ashamed, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing such Answers as would have satisfied all rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Men, to transcribe that <hi>wholo Chapter</hi> about the <hi>Cross into</hi> this <hi>New Book,</hi> just as it was there without offering to give one word of Reply [except that scrap of an Answer about Baptism being <hi>perfect without the Sign of the Cross</hi>] to Mr. <hi>Dean</hi>'s <hi>Answers</hi> to his <hi>Plea for Peace.</hi> But here I must recollect my self, that it was not worth Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> while to trouble himself with giving Answers to the <hi>Dean</hi> in <hi>this New Book,</hi> he tells us in his third Page, that to some part of his <hi>Plea for Peace indeed. Some meer Impertinent-Noise</hi> was made by <hi>some one that is confuted;</hi> which betwixt you and I, is a very pretty Character of the Writings of such <hi>Persons</hi> as the <hi>Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> and Dr. <hi>Sherlock;</hi> whom the <hi>Papists</hi> have not found to be such ignorant, or <hi>impertinent</hi> Men, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> did, but this is the temper of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and it is as impossible to cure
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97725:12"/>him of his Vanity, as of his Passion and Virulency.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Article, I would desire you to compare Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Plea for Peace</hi> from Pag. 177. to p. 181. with the 12th. Chapter of this his new Book; you will see reason why I say this Book was unneces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, since the things in both are the very same, no other differance but that <hi>that</hi> was by way of a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, <hi>this new one in</hi> Dialogue: I must now give you one of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Reasons for <hi>Laymen's</hi> Non-Conformity, and it shall be the <hi>Corporation Oath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon all that would enjoy the Priviledges of the Corporation,</hi> this is a special Reason, and is just such as the rest in his Book, it had been indeed direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his purpose, if every man that was allowed to be a Member of our Church, had been obliged to take the <hi>Corporation Oath;</hi> if all the People that live in the Villages throughout <hi>England,</hi> nay if all that live in any Towns that are Incorporate must have taken that <hi>Oath,</hi> or must not have come to Church, it had been a <hi>Just Plea</hi> for <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> in them who think the <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration-Oath</hi> unlawful; but that a man cannot come to Church and Communicate there in the Offices, because he cannot take the <hi>Corporation-Oath</hi> to qualifie him for example sake for <hi>Sheriff</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> is such Logick as no body will own or knows any thing of but Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His two Reasons just before this, to wit his 10th. and 11th. are of the same stamp, and indeed his whole <hi>dozen</hi> of Laymens Reasons are all alike, that is Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, who minds little else than to make a great shew, and manages his business by the Number not by the Weight of Arguments, or else I am sure it had been too hard a task for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to have mustered up <hi>Twelve Reasons</hi> why Laymen cannot conform to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97725:13"/>our Church, while all his Learning and Skill cannot help him to <hi>one</hi> Substantial Reason for Laymen's <hi>Non-Conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having now done with the <hi>Three Reasons</hi> I promised to give you an account of, and shewn you how you may convince your self of the <hi>unnecessariness</hi> of this <hi>New Book</hi> of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> even by the perusal only of his <hi>Pleas for Peace,</hi> I will pass now to my <hi>Second Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that this Book was altogether as <hi>Unseasonable</hi> as it was unnecessary.</p>
            <p>Within these last twenty Years or little more, there hath been nothing so much in some Mens mouths and in their Papers as <hi>Petitions for Peace, Pleas for Peace,</hi> the most <hi>Passionate Wishes</hi> for <hi>Concord,</hi> and <hi>Suplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons even upon their knees</hi> that they might be heard, for Accommodation, and yet to the unhappiness both of Church and State we have found no good to come of all these good words: One cannot but be even uneasie to know how Discord should continue, where there has been so much of temper, and such an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest Zeal for <hi>Concord;</hi> either the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> have been deaf to all <hi>Petitions for Peace,</hi> and inflexible and obstinate against healing such a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision in the Nation by some mild concessions, and abatements of what they themselves judged not abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely necessary; or those People on the other hand that talked so much of Peace, and Union, and Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, meant nothing less than what they said, but while they gave good words with their mouths, had War in their hearts, and were resolved either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the <hi>Constitution of the Church,</hi> or to keep up an eternal feud against Her.</p>
            <p>It is too easie to find where the guilt lies, and <hi>which side</hi> hath been really, notwithstanding all their talk,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97725:13"/>the true cause of the present Divisions being kept up to the height they are in. Only recollect to the time of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Plot,</hi> when it was hoped that it would have proved a happy juncture for an <hi>Ʋnion</hi> among <hi>Protestants,</hi> while all People were possessed with such apprehensions of very great dangers from Popery; most People thought that such a season would have invited, and of it self without any other Arguments have perswaded Protestants to a better understanding of themselves and one another, and that the Moderate <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> would have taken this favourable opportunity to apply themselves to the <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Ʋnion,</hi> whom they might then hope to have found in a good temper and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position for reconciliation, while both sides were equally apprehensive of dangers from the Common Enemy.</p>
            <p>Did those <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> therefore who have so loudly, and so often proclaimed to the World their earnest desire for <hi>Concord,</hi> their pursuit after <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Ʋnion</hi> lay hold of this favourable Opportunity, and address themselves to the Church of <hi>England</hi> for a happy Accommodation upon mutual Condescensions: No Sir, you know that they were so far from it, that when <hi>some</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> spake to them of it, <hi>They held back,</hi> and instead of such a beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour towards the Church as such a time did require, the <hi>Church of England</hi> her self was made <hi>Popish,</hi> infamous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels were daily thrown out against her.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dean</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> has given such an History of that time and affair, as will be a lasting Monument to the World,
<note place="margin">In the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his unreasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness of Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>p.</hi> 34, 35, 36, 37, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </note> how real some men were then, who had talked so much of <hi>Peace.</hi> I am confident he writes there what he was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of by his own experience, <hi>We were still in hopes</hi> (says he, speaking of that juncture of the Popish Plot) <hi>that Men</hi> so <hi>Wise,</hi> so <hi>
                  <hi>Self-denying</hi> as the Non-Conformist Ministers represent themselves to the World, would in so critical a time, have made some steps on advances towards an Ʋnion with us,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97725:14"/>at least to have let us know their sense of the present State of things, and their readiness to joyn with us, as far as they could, against the assaults of a Common Enemy. Instead</hi> of this, <hi>those we discoursed with, seem'd <hi>farther off than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</hi> and when we lest expected such a blow, under the name of a <hi>Plea for Peace,</hi> out comes a Book, which far better deserved the Title of, <hi>A Plea for Disorder and Seperarion.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already given you the Dean's further Character of this <hi>Book,</hi> but this was not all, for as Mr. <hi>Dean</hi> goes on in this History, <hi>But as though this had not been enough, to shew what Enemies to <hi>Peace</hi> Men may be under the pretence of it, not long after the same Author sets forth another Book with this Title, <hi>The True and only way of Concord of all the Christian Churches;</hi>
               </hi> and what Mr. <hi>Dean</hi>'s Sense was of these two Books, you may find just after the mention of them. <hi>When I looked into these Books, and saw the Design of them, I was mightily concerned, and infinitely surprized, that a Person of his Reputation for Piety, of his Age and Experience in the World, and such a <hi>Lover of Peace</hi> as he had always professed himself; and one who tells the World so often of his <hi>Dying</hi> and of the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, should think of leaving <hi>two such Firebrands</hi> behind him, as both these Books will appear to any one who duly considers them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Sir, who is it that should be guilty of writing two such pernicious and mischievous Books, and at so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seasonable a juncture, but our Friend Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who has <hi>Written</hi> and <hi>begg'd</hi> so much for <hi>Peace;</hi> the very same Man who in our days is now a second time guilty of the same mischievous and unseasonable Practice.</p>
            <p>You see Sir, by this account how earnest <hi>they</hi> were for Peace and Union with the Church, at such a critical and dangerous juncture, as that of the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> was, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had talked and written so much formerly for it, but w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97725:14"/>have a greater instance at this very time of the <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Temper</hi> of some of our <hi>Non-Conformist Brethren,</hi> as to the matter of healing our present Divisions.</p>
            <p>In the Church of <hi>England</hi> there hath appeared for some Years just past, a general inclination towards giving ease to such Dissenters as cannot joyn with the Church upon any terms less than her destroying her whole Constitution, and making the Terms of Communion easier to those that can unite with Her; the Bishops themselves whom Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is so fierce against, as not to allow that such an Inclination could be in them, were not shy of owning this to the World, when a necessity did require it: It was the great Design of that <hi>Ensnaring Declaration</hi> of the Late <hi>King for Liberty of Conscience</hi> to bring the <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to one of these difficulties, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to acknowledge and act under the <hi>Kings Dispensing Power,</hi> by dispersing and reading that Declaration, or to have made them appear to the Body of the Dissenters as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinate against all tenderness towards them by their refusing to read it; and this Design was as easily baffled by the Bishops, who tho' they would not be brought upon any terms to own such a pernicious Dispensing Power in the King by consenting to read his Declaration, yet took care in their <hi>Famous Petition</hi> to Him, to let the World know, That <hi>they were not averse to the Publishing of the Declaration for want of due tenderness towards Dissenters, in relation to whom,</hi> they declared, <hi>they were willing to come to such a Temper as should be thought fit, when that matter came to be considered and setled in Parliament and Convocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Assurance</hi> to the Dissenters was not forgotten by the <hi>Reverend Bishops,</hi> when their troubles about that <hi>mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Declaration</hi> were over, but was <hi>renewed</hi> by <hi>Them</hi> in those <hi>Proposals of Advice to</hi> that <hi>King</hi> by most of the <hi>same Bishops,</hi> whom he had sent for up out of the Country
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97725:15"/>to advise with. I think it is in the 10th. or 11th. Article [for I have them not here with me] of those <hi>Proposals</hi> as they are Printed more exactly in the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Rochester's Second Letter</hi> to the <hi>Lord Chamberlain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when this first Parliament after those Promises made by the Bishops was set down, and a Motion made by an <hi>Honourable Peer</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that a Bill or Bills might be brought in for the <hi>ease of Dissenters, several</hi> of the <hi>Bishops</hi> did not only second the Motion, but the <hi>Bishops</hi> of <hi>St. Asaph</hi> and <hi>Ely, Glocester, Chichester,</hi> and <hi>Peterborough,</hi> made Speeches in the House upon it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the means of an <hi>Accommodation by improving and perfecting the Liturgy, and making some Terms of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more easie, and of ease to all Protestant Dissenters that cannot come up to those Terms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These are Instances beyond all Question of the <hi>Bishops Integrity</hi> in this business, when <hi>They promised tenderness to the Dissenters;</hi> and this Disposition was seen in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of the Inferiour <hi>Clergy</hi> also, I cannot but refer you for a full satisfaction herein, to the <hi>Publick Sermons</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ever since; I may appeal to the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Aldermen</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> ever since their <hi>Chappel</hi> at <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> was open, whether the Clergy did not discover in their Sermons before them, the same inclinations to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness towards all, and to Union with some of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Dissenters,</hi> and particularly Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">See his Sermon Preached before the Lord May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, <hi>Nov.</hi> 1688.</note> whom Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and some of his Brethren have taken so much pains to represent to the World as an Enemy to Peace, and a mighty favourer of Popery; and whether they did not earnestly advise others to the same Temper, and heartily pray that it might also be found among the Dissenters: The same Appeal I might make concerning those Sermons at Court before their Majesties, but most of them are in Print, and speak for themselves.</p>
            <p>And the same Temper did appear in their Conversation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97725:15"/>as well as in their Sermons, and I need give no farther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of their willingness for tenderness and Union, I ought to say of their Zeal for it, than the <hi>Letter to a Member of Parliament in favour of the Bill for Vniting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants;</hi> which was written while the Bill for Union was passing the Two Houses of Parliament, and which I do most earnestly recommend to the perusal of all Protestant Dissenters, and of them, who will notwithstanding all this which hath been said and done on the Church's side, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as I have heard some very lately do for want of true Information about these things) that the Church-men are not for Moderation towards Dissenters.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I think I have made it evident enough, what a general Disposition towards tenderness has appear'd on our side, the Bishops have inviolably observed the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and Assurances which they gave, the rest of the Clergy have discharged themselves faithfully herein, being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly willing, but many of them Zealous Promoters of an Union with some, and ease to all Dissenters, neither Books nor Papers against these things on our side, but every thing contrary. This is the Temper, and this is the Behaviour of the Bishops and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> in order to Peace and Union, and now I must enquire whether the same Temper has appear'd among the Dissenters, and whether their Behaviour has been of this kind: And here I cannot without Sorrow and Indignation tell you, that their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour has been since the late happy Revolution such, as cannot be reconciled with any Disposition to Peace or Concord; They have, I am affraid it will be to their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Infamy, Published within one quarter of a Year since this Revolution more Books, nay above twice as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Books against the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than they did during all the last Kings Reign against Popery, tho' they could not but see and own, that Popery was like to bear down all before it, and it seems might have done for all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97725:16"/>them, who amidst all the furious and numerous attacks of our Protestant Religion from the Popish Priests stood look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, as if they had been unconcerned Spectators as a show, and were as mute as Fishes, excepting only two Persons among them, who when the Controversie was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most at an end, writ two small Tracts upon the same Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Transubstantiation. They have begun the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie afresh against the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as if they were unwilling to allow any rest to those who had labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed so couragiously against Popery, but I dare undertake to foretel their success, that as they had less reason than the Papist to begin a Controversie against the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> so they will reap as little credit from it, since (bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed be God) as the Church of <hi>England</hi> wanted not of her Sons to Encounter and Triumph over Popery when it was in its greatest Power, and had the Countenance of the King for it, so she has those that can with as much ease baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle all the New-mustered Reasons for Non-Conformity. How often have we been told by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and others of them, that they are not against Episcopacy and Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and yet at this time, when we might have expected that they would have had some regard to the Peace and Union of our Nation, and to their own words, the very first Book they let fly against us, is against our Episcopacy it self, wherein they strike at our Episcopacy as unknown to the Church of Christ for the first Three Hundred years, the Author of this Book is dead some time ago, but the Party will not suffer the Book (as it ought) to have died with him, but Mr. <hi>Isaac Chauncy</hi> must usher it out into the World (in order to our Union at this time) with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the same tune of proving, that a Bishop in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles times, and for the space of the first Three Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Gospel-Church, was no more than a Pastor to one single Congregation. This Book is fit to impose up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on none but those that know not one Syllable of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97725:16"/>of the first Ages of the Church, and hath been as to the Substance of it answered already by the Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> in his Unreasonableness of Separation, <hi>Part</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 242, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by Dr. <hi>Maurice</hi> in the latter part of the Preface to his <hi>Vindication of the Primitive Church and Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesan Episcopacy,</hi> and in the Book it self, and I have leave to promise the World, that a compleat Answer to the whole will be finished and publisht shortly.</p>
            <p>Their second Book which they published against us, and from the same hand, was about Liturgies to shew the Novelty of them, and how long it was before any such were known or heard of in the Christian Church; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of Publishing these two Books is very easily seen, which I do not care to insist further upon here, since it is so plainly contrary to the repeated Professions of so many Non-Conformists: however I can assure you that these two Books are not like to do the Mischief which is intended by them, since this about Liturgies, as well as the other about Episcopacy, is under the Examination of a very Learned Person, and both the Answers may be expected by the end of <hi>Michaelmas-Term,</hi> or at the beginning of the next <hi>Term</hi> after <hi>Christmas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These two small Tracts about two particular Points were only to make way for two more voluminous Peices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the whole Controversie betwixt the Non-Conformists and the Church was to be reassumed at a time, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one thought it had been laid asleep, and that healing Principles and Concessions, would have been the study of both sides equally. The Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> I am confident did believe, that the angry Controversie against his excellent and well-design'd Sermon at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> in 1680. had been ended near seven years ago; and who would have expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that after so long a cessation of Arms, and at so unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable a juncture the World should have been troubled with that Controversie any more? You must therefore learn
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97725:17"/>to wonder at nothing in some Men, the Mountain is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd at last, and one Mr. <hi>Gilbert Rule</hi> is deliver'd of a <hi>Rational Defence of Non-Conformity,</hi> in answer to Dr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fleet's Ʋnreasonableness of Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have had this Book with me into the Country, but cannot now give you my Judgment of it; by what I have read in it; I can readily find, that the Excellent <hi>Dean</hi> needs not trouble himself with taking notice of it, and I hope he never will; however Mr. <hi>Rule</hi> ought not to expect an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer yet, nor to complain, tho' it be seven years before he receive it, since his own was so long in bringing forth; and betwixt You and I, it will take up no very small part of that time to get through Mr. <hi>Rule</hi>'s Book, not for the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of it, but for a worse Reason or two, which I will leave you to guess at.</p>
            <p>It will perchance be replyed to this, that the Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists ought not to bear the blame, if such Men as Mr. <hi>Rule</hi> will be troubling the World so unseasonably with their Controversies and Defences: But what will they be able to say for the next Author I must mention, their great Oracle Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who has written, and said, and begg'd so much for Peace, and for Accommodation, that he should be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of so much Indiscretion, and unseasonable Zeal, as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to exasperate Dissenters against the Church, and the Church-men against Dissenters, at a time when he could not but know, that there were such general preparations and dispositions for Peace every where, and that he from whom of all Dissenters living such a thing was least expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, should not only Publish but take such care to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented to the Members of Parliament this violent unseaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Book which you have sent me.</p>
            <p>I must own to you, that it hath very much lessen'd the esteem I have had for Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> to find him thus sowing Discord and Division, and such an Enemy to Peace, and in so small a disposition for it, as this Book shews him to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97725:17"/>notwithstanding all his former Professions for Peace. I cannot reconcile this Book or the temper of it, either with Charity or Christianity.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble you with the fry of little Pamphlets thrown about at the same juncture against our Church, some of which I have seen, and believe there are more which I have not. I will only ask now, whether the Temper and Promises of our Bishops, the Sermons and Discourses of our Clergy, or the Writings and Pamphlets of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Clarkson,</hi> of <hi>Rule,</hi> and the like Published since this happy Revolution discover better inclinations to Peace and Union; and whether any thing can be so likely to breed further mischief, and to prevent all Accommodation as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s starting the Controversie so unseasonably at this time.</p>
            <p>I hope in God, that whatever Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Intentions were by his Publishing such a Book at this juncture, and by taking such care to have them presented to all Parliament Men and to others, particularly to several of the Clergy of <hi>London,</hi> and to such of them as had been his Antagonists in this very Controversie, neither the Bishops will mind Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> or his Book, nor the Clergy be provoked by it to lay aside their Dispositions to Peace and Accommodation, but that our Church may have the Glory, and the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of doing some men good against their wills.</p>
            <p>I think, Sir, that I have shewn you sufficiently how very unseasonable this Book of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s was for those peaceable designs which have been on foot a long time, and published to the World by the Bishops Famous Petition for above this last twelve Month; I have now but one other Reflection to make upon it, that it is as <hi>Vnaccountable</hi> a Book, as it was <hi>Vnseasonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One would have expected that the great age Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is arrived to, and the continual complaints that were made of his indulging and giving up himself upon the least occasion
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97725:18"/>to heats and passion in his controversial Books, had taught him to restrain himself for the future, and to refrain all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deciences either towards Persons or Things: but this Book of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s is a deplorable instance how deaf some can be to the best advice, and how far Passion can become habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual to some as even to be Nature in them, and what they cannot conquer or avoid. His Passion in this Book hurries him sometimes so far as to make him forget Truth and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, and to sacrifice both them to his Indiscretion.</p>
            <p>Tho' I know you do not wonder at such things in Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> yet I am sensible a great many will, and that all his Favourers and Friends will accuse me immediately of Injustice and Calumny against an innocent Man.</p>
            <p>How innocent Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is as to those Reflections I have made, they themselves shall be the Judges if they please, the World however will, and if such things be not in this Book as I charge Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> with, and it be not altogether as unaccountable a Book as I affirm it to be, I will begg Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, Theirs, and the World's pardon.</p>
            <p>To prove the heat he was in, when he Published this Book, and the strange Passion which hurries him through it, I will not trouble any one to look into the Book it self, or so much as to open it, let him but read this Title Page it self, and then pass sentence upon the Book or Me. <hi>The English Non-Conformity as under King</hi> Charles <hi>II. and King</hi> James <hi>II. truly Stated and Argued, by</hi> Richard Baxter, <hi>who earnestly beseecheth Rulers, and Clergy, not to Divide and Destroy the Land, and cast their own Souls on the dreadful Guilt and Punishment of <hi>Qational</hi> PERJƲRY <hi>Lying, deliverate Covenanting to Sin against God,</hi> corrupt his Church, and not amend, nor by Laws or <hi>Blind Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> to reproach Faithful Ministers of Christ, and Judge them to Scorn and Beggery, and <hi>To Lie and Die in Jails as Rogues,</hi> and so to strengthen <hi>Profaneness, Popery</hi> and Schism, and all for want of Willingness and Patience to read
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97725:18"/>and hear their just defence; while they can spend much more time in Sin and Vanity. The Author humbly begs that he and <hi>His Books of Vnconfutable Defence</hi> of a mistaken persecuted Cause may not be Witnesses against them for such great and wilful sin to their Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is I must needs say, the warmest Title Page I ever read, and so will you, and all those Lords and Gentlemen Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Book was presented to, here is nothing but Passion and Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on throughout.</p>
            <p>And the same heat that is upon the Title Page, is carried through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Book, if he has occasion to speak of the Bishops and Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or to dispute any point with them in it, Diocesans, Prelates, Book-makers are the Bishops Titles with him, but for the rest of the <hi>Clergy</hi> he knows not how to call them ill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. One while they are a Multitude of raw ignorant Fellows or Lads, in another place they are ignorant ungodly Lads; What would Forreigners think of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> of those nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Learned Tracts which were Published within these last four years against Popery in <hi>England,</hi> should they read these Characters of our Bishops and Clergy in the Book of one, who lives among them, who lives in <hi>London</hi> it self, and must certainly know, that the Characters are deserved which so Pious, so Conscientious a Man, who believes a Judgment and a Hell does venture to give of them, the least that such could believe must be, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and his Brethren <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> are the only supporters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Piety and Learning in <hi>England,</hi> and that every one of those so many Learned Books lately Published against <hi>Popery</hi> were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by them, and that none of them could be the Works of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant ungodly Lads. But if I were to argue with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> upon this point, I would fain know what reason or what necessity there was for such strange and unaccountable language towards the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> would not the Reasons and Arguments in his Book against us have been as strong and as clear, tho' he should have used all decent behaviour towards our Bishops and Clergy in it, and had omitted such ignominious Names and Characters: Such Language is so far from being necessary to make an Argument good, or a deduction plain, that it makes the World suspect, that the strength and whole force of such a Man's Argument lies in the Nick-name and ignominious Character.</p>
            <p>His Indecencies towards his Betters, and his Brethren however, is much more excusable than his Passionate rudeness towards things
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97725:19"/>Sacred, towards one of our Sacraments: when he is up in his heat and violence, then Baptism it self must be called (as an Atheist or Scoffer at Religion does) <hi>Water and Words</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">P. 26.</note> and he goes on raving against the Church's Power to admit Infants indiscrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately to Baptism; If (says he) <hi>it be meerly volendo, as if Heaven</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">P. 63.</note>
               <hi>were at their will, why do they not sit at home, and make a deed of Gift of Heaven to the Infants at the Antipodes and of all the World.</hi> And a little lower, <hi>He that can believe to day that God hath made a gift of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to all Infants that any body will Baptize, may easily believe to morrow, that he will not cast away the rest meerly because no Carrier will bring them in, or because no body will wash them, and say over them the words of Baptism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this indecent and unbecoming manner does Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> treat Baptism it self, in expressions so clownish as are fitter for a Porter's mouth than a Divine's: if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> thought himself witty in these passages, I know what rank of Men to range him among, they do not become any sort of Gown, nor Men of any Ingenuity or Breeding.</p>
            <p>But these Indecencies towards Persons, and Sacred Things may be much better accounted for than his Insults upon Truth and Modesty, and his Violation of them. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is pleased (when he is discoursing the Matter whether the Church or the Dissenters did more probably serve the Designs of Popery) to grow very warm about it, and to appeal to experience, <hi>I think,</hi> says he,
<note n="(c)" place="margin">P. 222.</note>
               <hi>ere long you are like to be convinc'd more effectually than by writing, which Party is liker to bring in Popery, and to turn Papist</hi> and asks the Question very boldly, <hi>Who hath done and suffer'd more to keep Popery out,</hi> that is, <hi>Churchmen</hi> or <hi>Dissenters.</hi> I will joyn issue with Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> upon this Question, and will appeal to the World, whether it is the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> Men or the <hi>Dissenters</hi> that have done or suffer'd more to keep out Popery; The late Kings Reign is the time by which we can try this cause, then it was that Popery appear'd barefac't, and endeavour'd by Places and Preferments as well as by Pen and Pulpit to prevail over the Nation; We will examine then first, who did most to keep out Popery; when the Protestant Religion was assaulted by the Popish Priests, both from the Press and from the Pulpit; Did the <hi>Dissenters</hi> enter the lists with them? did they countermine Popery from their Pulpits? They dare not deny that it was the Churchmen, and they alone that manag'd the whole Controversie against the Popish Books, they dare not deny that the province of Preaching down Popery during the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97725:19"/>Popish Reign was left entirely to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> Pulpits, that for their own Part they did not offer to Preach against the Kings Religion, but were wholly silent therein, that for their Part instead of writing Books against Popery, they writ in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of it by consequence while they flattered by their Address a <hi>Popish</hi> King in his dispensing with our Laws, and breaking in upon the Establishment of the Protestant Religion among us. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> himself knows one that was writing an Address to the <hi>Popish</hi> King, while the Churchmen were defending their own, and exposing his Religion; There were abundance of excellent and very bold Sermons Preached against <hi>Popery</hi> even during the last four years of the Reign of <hi>Popery,</hi> there were above 200 Discourses publisht against <hi>Popery</hi> during that Reign; I must now ask Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> two very short Questions; <hi>First,</hi> Who they were that preached those Sermons, and writ those Books? His Conscience cannot but make him confess that they were the Members of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Who they were then that have <hi>done more to keep out Popery?</hi> Let him but read what he said in his Book, and ask his Conscience <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Question, <hi>What is Truth?</hi> Let us now see whether <hi>Churchmen</hi> or <hi>Dissenters Suffer'd</hi> more to keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> and here I need only ask Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> two or three Questions; Were those Noblemen and Gentlemen <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters</hi> that left all their profitable places, and were closetted and turn'd out of all Commissions, because they would neither promise nor consent to take off the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests?</hi> Were those <hi>Churchmen</hi> that were put into their Places and Commissions? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, Were those that were try'd and Suspended by the Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Commission <hi>Dissenters?</hi> Was the Bishop of <hi>London</hi> such, the Vicechancellor of <hi>Cambridge</hi> such, or the Fellows of <hi>Magdalen Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> in <hi>Oxon</hi> such? Lastly, Were those seven Bishops that were sent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and try'd for resisting the destructive dispensing Power <hi>Dissenters?</hi> Were any of those who were Displaced, Sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, or Imprison'd <hi>Non-Conformists?</hi> Or were any <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists</hi> either Displaced, or Suspended or Imprisoned? Did not they Address, Consent and Concur to lay aside the <hi>Test?</hi> Were not <hi>Lob,</hi> and <hi>Alsop,</hi> and <hi>Penn</hi> become the Ministers of State? I could ask Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> some more as uneasie Questions, I will only desire to know with what face he could talk at that rate in his Book, and yet know all these things; I will only put him in mind of a say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his own which he uses in this very Dispute, <hi>The Impudency of some Men is the shame of depraved humane Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:97725:20"/>
            <p>I have now but a small part of my last charge against Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> upon my hands, that he hath not consulted Modesty any more than Truth in this his Book, this is a nice matter, and almost as indecent to be repeated, as it was in him for to write it.</p>
            <p>In one part of his Book he is making the Comparison betwixt the lives of those who go to Church, and his Friends that stay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and cannot indure to hear that <hi>Churchmen</hi> should be better than <hi>Dissenters,</hi> and then asks whether the badness of those who stay away from the Church is in any Vice, after which comes the Modest Lecture I must mention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here are,</hi> some say, <hi>many hundreds that Practice Physick in</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: <hi>The Posts, Walls, and Gates</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">P. 220.</note>
               <hi>are stickt with Physicians offers to cure the</hi> Lecherous Pox: <hi>To day I read</hi> Kirleu's <hi>Bill,</hi> that saith, <hi>he hath Cured Eight Hundred of that Disease. I dare bet with you all the Money I have, that if you enquire, not eight, or perhaps two of that Eight Hundred were</hi> Puritans, <hi>or such as you now cast out for</hi> Non-Conformists (<hi>unless you call</hi> Papists <hi>or such other,</hi> Non-Conformists) <hi>except any of them were Wives that catcht it of Husbands that are of your Church or Purishes, and not of us; or Husbands that catcht of such Conformable</hi> (<hi>or</hi> Papist) <hi>Wives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You see, and cannot without laughing read how very critical and nice Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is upon the matter, but he should have been as tender of a thing called <hi>Modesty;</hi> such a Description is fitter for <hi>Aretine</hi> than Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> but some Men can allow themselves in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, tho' it be never so ridiculous and immodest together.</p>
            <p>These are the Reflections I design'd to make upon Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi>'s Book, and if you have read thus far, you will be able to justifie me in every one of them, that this Book ought not have been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished at all, since it was so unnecssary, so unseasonable, and such a passionate unaccountable Book; whether the writing this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will do any service to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> by shewing him how very unhappy he has been herein I cannot divine; nor whether it will make him more cautious for the future. One thing I cannot but beg of Heaven for him, that God would forgive him the publishing this Book; and to this Prayer I must add this wish, that when ever Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is call'd out of this World, this and all the rest of his Controversial Books may be buried with him, that so those Books which have done no good in this Age, may never be able to do mischief in the Next. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours <hi>N. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>